participant yeah there hi nice to meet
you
very very nice so i might
start now so i have the extreme honor to
introduce professor carl fristen who is
professor for neuroduty at university
college london and he is scientific
director of the welcome test center for
neuroimaging in london
he is one of the
leading experts for brain imaging and in
particular he invented the key
technology spm
which is cited as a single paper more
often than the publications or the
citations of others in their whole
lifetime so he is regarded as one of the
top 10 most influential neuroscientists
and i think personally that this
research is a superb example of how
formal mathematical modelling and
machine learning can help to understand
key questions of mankind so how the
brain works
professor fristen is a recipient of the
first young investigators involved in
human brain mapping fellow of rural
society fellow of academy of medical
sciences recipient of me never golden
brain award and actually the awards are
so many that i would eat up your time
therefore rather as an elaborating on
your cv please allow me to give the word
to you and to learn more about active
inference i'm pleased to
attend your talk and everyone else
thank you thank you
it's a great pleasure to be here and i
very much
welcome the opportunity to speak to you
today i'm going to talk about active
inference and ask a question
what is optimal about behavior and in
particular
are there different kinds of optimality
specifically bayesian optimality in
terms of those things that we aspire to
and
the information gain consequent upon our
sentient behavior
my talk's going to have two parts to it
i'm going to first of all set up the
framework in terms of self-evidencing
namely action and perception in the
service of maximizing the evidence for
our generative models of the world i'm
going to motivate that in terms of
normative accounts of sentient behavior
and related specifically to things like
artificial intelligence and machine
learning
the second part of the talk will use
simulations to illustrate technically
the kind of message passing entailed by
the first principal account of the first
half of the talk and i want to conclude
but with a special focus on epistemic
foraging responding to affordances that
denote
information gain
following a particular course of action
or policy
so
self-evidencing active inference is
predicated on the notion that there's
one underlying objective function such
that we can read perception and action
as a process of optimization so what are
we optimizing effectively we're
optimizing the log probability of some
outcomes given a generative model or
more simply me
who would anticipate those outcomes and
clearly that's almost a tautological
specification of the kinds of outcomes i
expect to encounter so we can read this
as those
outcomes that have value and
we can from that reading
motivate a description in terms of
reinforcement learning
in engineering optimal control theory
and if we were an economist this would
be something like expected utility
theory
what i will go on to unpack is
an approximation a bound approximation
to this kind of value
that i'm going to refer to as a
variation of free energy or more simply
free energy
interestingly the negative of this free
energy or value
is
self-information or surprisal or more
simply surprise and information theory
so this provides a normative account of
sentient behavior in terms of things
like the principle of maximum efficiency
or the principle of minimum redundancy
the inframax principle and indeed the
free energy principle itself
that in turn is interesting because the
long-term average of surprisal or
surprise or self-information is entropy
so if we imagine that action and
perception or always trying to maximize
value or minimize surprise then on
average it will look as if action and
perception are also trying to minimize
entropy and that of course is a holy
grail of many accounts of behavior in
terms of self-organization
uh particularly synergetics and of
course if i were a physiologist this
would just be a statement of homeostasis
keeping physiological states within
viable bounds resisting the second law
where those physiological states would
be dispersed and i would dissipate uh
dissolve or and possibly die
there's a final perspective on this
quantity which i'm going to leverage
and that's a much more statistical uh
perspective namely the probability of
outcomes given me as a model
and in basin statistics that will be
known as bayesian model evidence and
from that we can link to accounts of
brain function in terms of the bayesian
brain hypothesis
evidence accumulation perceptions
hypothesis testing predictive coding and
so on so those are
if you like some of the
normative theories
that can all be subsumed by
putting in play a particular objective
function and the form of the objective
function that i'm going to consider is a
free energy that comprises a negative
energy and an entropy here um for those
of you not familiar with this you can
see this as essentially a statement of
james's maximum entropy principle so
that we want to effectively maximize the
entropy
of our beliefs about the states of the
world that are generating outcomes
under certain constraints and those
constraints we will see
are described by the likelihood of those
outcomes given those states that's
usually hidden or latent states in the
world and our prior beliefs about the
states of affairs uh generating our
observable outcomes
so
in machine learning
many people will be familiar with this
as an evidence lower bound so i can
unpack this free energy functional its
functional form
in terms of an expected log evidence
simply the probability of some outcomes
um under a given model plus a
colbecca liblar divergence
that can never be less than zero and
that constitutes
a band on the log evidence giving me
this notion of an elbow or an evidence
lower bound
that's i think an important perspective
because i'm defining the evidence in
relation to a genitive model
i have now
at the start an explainable and
interpretable
account of how any data that i'm trying
to classify or
use to infer the causes
generates those data so basically i
should have four free explainable and
interpretable
artificial intelligence
what we will see is it will also for
free from this bayesian perspective and
leverage a design optimality in terms of
optimal experimental design
which we can understand as
augmenting an abductive inference and
indeed if we take
that abduction through from
inference to learning
auto-poetic self-constructing
self-teaching
kind of inference and learning
which in principle would lead to a first
principle account of data foraging and
epistemics and possibly generalized ai
or
agi
i want to
look at this objective function from a
different perspective simply by
rearranging the terms so all i've done
here is just move the terms around
and expressed it
in a way that would be more familiar to
statisticians so this same objective
function can be written down as a
mixture of accuracy and complexity where
the accuracy is simply the expected log
likelihood of some observable data given
their causes
minus the complexity that is simply the
kl divergence between my posterior
beliefs q and some prior beliefs about
the states generating those data
so that's an intuitive
view of this objective functional the
complexity term plays a key role here
many people will recognize this in terms
of occam's principle in the brain this
translates into things like functional
specialization and redundancy
minimization efficient coding
from an
engineering perspective
this complexity also can be understood
in terms of minimizing the computational
cost literally the degree to which i
have to change my mind and going from my
prior beliefs to my posterior beliefs in
order to provide an accurate account of
the data at hand
implicit in those prizes of course are
parsimonious explanations and beliefs
possibly heuristics about the generation
of the data that i'm trying to explain
from the point of view of thermodynamics
that computational complexity translates
directly into a thermodynamic or in
biology a metabolic cost via things like
the czarzinski equality and landauer's
principle which put it very simply means
that if i'm doing it in the right kind
of way i'm doing it very quickly and i'm
doing it with the minimum use of energy
what i really want to do though is to
take that sort of
partition
of the right kinds of inference and
actions
in the moment and think about the free
energy in the future following a
particular
act upon the world and what we're going
to see
when we consider self-evidencing in the
future is the emergence of again this
dual perspective on an objective
function in terms of optimal bayesian
design and that we will see
maximizes the accuracy i expect
following a move or a sampling of some
data
while the expected complexity
corresponds to optimal bayesian decision
in relation to some prior preferences
and the two together constitute this
self-evidencing so that the base optimal
design perspective and base optimal
decisions are two aspects of the same
thing two sides of the same coin which
is this underlying imperative to
maximize this evidence lower band
so to make that more heuristic let me
just um
pose a question to the audience imagine
you're an owl and you're hungry and if
we were in person
i would
actually ask someone in the audience to
say what are you going to do next and
almost invariably somebody somebody
correctly replies well i'm going to look
for my food i'm going to search for my
prey
and then predate
that prey
that simple answer
has a lot of implications for the choice
of the account of sentient behavior
if it were the case
that
i were
simply choosing my actions
in order to maximize some value function
of the states that would ensue say s of
t plus one
following a particular action
i could formulate optimal behavior in
terms of a state action policy so i
would be choosing those behaviors or
those control variables that maximized
my value function my state the action
value function
of the consequences of behaving and
thereby elaborate an optimal policy
however
the simple answer i am going to search
for food means that this may not be the
best way of formulating optimal behavior
so why is that well
to search is to resolve uncertainty
about where my food is but uncertainty
is an attribute of a belief
therefore that tells us that perhaps the
better kind of objective function or
certainly its functional form
is a functional in the sense that is a
function of a function where that
function is a belief so put that simply
optimal action may depend upon states of
the world
or
on beliefs about states of the world so
i'm if you like formalizing that in
terms of actions that maximize
a functional g
of beliefs about states of the world
given a particular behavior
furthermore
thinking about the searching for food
example
it matters the order in which i do
things so
i can either try to eat my prey and then
search for it or search for it identify
where it is and then try to eat it
and that ordered aspect leads us into
the notion of sequential policy
optimization and technically
that has implications for the functional
form
of a normative account based upon an
objective functional
and i've
formulated that here in terms of
maximizing a path integral of a
functional of
the beliefs about states of the world
that would ensue under a particular
policy where a policy here now is read
as a sequence of actions or controls
which is distinct from the state action
policy here and the reason that i'm
trying to emphasize the difference
between these two things is to
deliberately introduce a dialectic
between accounts of sentient behavior
based on melbourne's optimality
principle
versus this path integral of an energy
functional um which in physics would be
known as an action so what we're talking
about basically is a principle of least
action
that accounts for optimal action in
terms of beliefs about states versus an
optimality principle that does not and
many of you will recognize
the different
themes and schemes that arise under
these two um complementary approaches to
optimizing behavior so for example under
belmont's optimality principle would
have optimal control theory dynamic
processing
deep rl um bayesian rl basin decision
theory state action policy durations and
so on a slightly different perspective
emerges under a principle of least
action
including active inference
and probably more interestingly
artificial curiosity on and in robotics
this will be known as intrinsic
motivation i'm going to cast that in
terms of optimal bayesian design that
for free becomes part of sequential
policy optimization and the treatment of
partially observed uh markov decision
processes
um so what is this free energy um and
it's associated functional um that
underwrites a principle at least action
for a physics of sentience a
a bayesian mechanics that explains um or
best accounts for optimal behavior well
here i've just rewritten the um the free
energy functional
function my parties
in terms of accuracy and complexity so
this is the kl divergence we've already
spoken about and the accuracy the log
likelihood of outcomes given states and
here just by moving these terms around
we can see immediately how this also
translates into an evidence bound in the
sense this is another non-negative kl
divergence and this is the um the
evidence associated with particular
outcomes
the reason i've written this out is to
disclose
to show what i think is quite a
beautiful mapping between this quantity
and the same quantity that would be
expected
given
i have committed to a particular act
now the reason that the ins the expected
gets into the game and we move from f to
g
is that before i i have acted i don't
have the sensory outcomes available so
now i have to take an expectation
of the free energy
under my posterior predicted beliefs
about what i would observe if i made
that move
and
what one sees is that the expected
complexity um translates into something
called risk the expected accuracy
becomes something called or negative
expected accuracy becomes ambiguity
while the evidence found in log evidence
um can be read as an intrinsic and
extrinsic value respectively so let me
just try and relate that to
well-established um normative accounts
of behavior um first of all let's just
focus on the intrinsic value and pretend
we had no prior beliefs about the
outcomes that characterized me um
sometimes referred to as prior
preferences so let's ignore
the extrinsic value the prior
preferences and see what is left and
what is left is effectively
an expected divergence between beliefs
about states of the world
before and after observing their
consequences
and this is just the degree to which my
uncertainty as a result has
been resolved by committing to this
particular policy
another way of expressing that is the
information gain or the epistemic
affordance um due to this policy in the
visual search literature that's known as
bayesian surprise mathematically it's
just the mutual information between the
states the world
causes and their consequences their
observable
consequences in the future conditioned
upon a particular policy
um
what i'm going to do now is take away a
particular
kind of uncertainty
and remove it from the table
and the the the
uncertainty i'm talking about is the
ambiguity so if i remove ambiguity and
pretend that i can see directly all
these hidden states these latent states
generating data then i can ignore this
and we just are left with the risk term
so what's a risk term well that's
another kl divergence and it just scores
the difference between
beliefs about states in the future given
that i have committed to this policy and
my prior preferences so it's just the
difference between what i anticipate
will happen if i do this
versus the kinds of outcomes that i
would prefer or expect myself to
encounter
and in engineering this is just kl
control in economics it's risk sensitive
because we are not we are no longer
dealing um with ambiguity
so let me make a final move here and
take away the risk part in the sense
that there is no
relative uncertainty about the outcomes
of my behavior and what are we left with
well we're left with this term here
which is back to this um value term in
the first review of normative theories
the extrinsic value that reflects my
prior preferences about the kinds of
observations i expect to solicit
irrespective of how i behave and from
this we can
interpret
optimal behavior in terms of an expected
value
for example an economics expected
utility theory so there's an interesting
relationship between
this account of optimal behavior
and the bellman optimality account of
optimal behavior that arises when i
successfully remove different kinds of
uncertainty from the problem and in fact
we can now repair that dialectic between
the government optionality principle and
the principle at least action simply by
saying that the latter
is a special case of the principle of
least action when there's no uncertainty
to worry about
the
ensuing
computational architecture that we now
use to simulate and understand sentient
behavior in the neurosciences
and in our simulations of
active imprints
is shown on this slide so
in brief we can think of
outcomes being gathered by our sensory
organs
being taken into the brain for example
to be assimilated to build posterior
bayesian beliefs that maximize this
evidence lower bound about hidden states
external states beyond technically what
is a markov blanket separating the
external states from internal brain
states
to optimize our beliefs to get the best
approximation or best guess about the
states generating those outcomes and
then we use our beliefs about the
external
latent states to evaluate well what
would happen if i did that in terms of
the expected free energy and we've seen
that we can unpack that or carve it into
risk and ambiguity terms and then form
beliefs about the most likely policies
that we are pursuing and then we can
supplement action from those policies
and generate a new observation from the
world out there and the cycle the action
perception uh cycle can continue
so in short polycystic policy selection
uh can be cast as maximization of an
expected free energy uh whereas
perceptual inference can be thought of
as uh as maximizing this
evidence lower bound
so all i've said is essentially we have
at hand a variational principle at least
action
that subsumes
both the epistemic information part of
optimal behavior
and
the that which can be ascribed to the
extrinsic or the expected value under
some prior preferences and together they
simply mean that we are
choosing those actions
inferring the plans
the policies that maximize expected free
energy uh and this is very close
of course to things uh notions
um like planning and control um as
inference but in a way that has this
dual aspect of
of both
trying to be information seeking at the
same time
being reward seeking or goal seeking
in our
epistemic responses
so let me briefly illustrate
what implications
that formulation that sort of least
action formulation has
for belief updating the brain and
subsequent behavior and
i've written this down um
formally in a way that i thought might
be revealing for people in computer
science and to designing message passing
schemes what what this slide is meant to
show is that
if i had a generative model
of how
hidden states unobservable latent states
out there
generate outcomes then i can always
write it down as a probabilistic
graphical model so for example
we could
assume a discrete state-space model a um
a hidden markup model or a markov
decision process partially observed of
the following form where the world is in
different states one of a number of
different states and they move from one
stage to the next point in time
in accord with a probability transition
matrix that itself depends upon the
particular sequence of
actions that i prosecute the plan um
that itself depends upon the expected
free energy and once i know the states
of the world i can then generate through
a likelihood
mapping here denoted by the a matrix
some observable outcomes so this would
be a generative model for a partially
observed
markov decision process that is
inherently inactive in the sense that
the state transitions depend upon my
action
which itself depends upon the expected
free energy and you know please ignore
these equations here they're just
articulating um this
example a fairly generic or universal
example of discrete state space
models of the way that my
observable outcomes my sensory
information could be generated
this is nice because if i can write down
a probabilistic graphical model there
will always exist a factor graph and in
this instance a
forney or normal style factor graph and
that is the cousin or the conjugate of
this graphical model here where the
nodes become edges and the edges become
nodes we don't need to worry about that
that we need to know is if we can write
this down we can always write this down
what does writing this down mean well it
entails a very precise a concrete and
crisp
description of the message passing that
will be needed in order to infer all the
unknowns here basically states the world
that i don't know and what i am doing
the policies
i can infer all of these by passing
messages around
over these edges that now correspond to
the run the unknowns the random
variables um given the um the
parameterized generative model in terms
of
the prize the probability transition
matrices and the likelihood it's naming
the likelihood mappings between uh
causes and consequences
and i've just written down this message
passing here in terms of belief updating
belief updating of things that we don't
know states of the world under a
particular policy and the policy which
is just a soft max function of the
expected free energy here
um and the expressions that inherit from
the um the form the functional forms of
the previous slides written down in
terms of linear algebra and the
matrices and tensors
of the generative model here
those updates which are just off the
shelf uh variational message passing
updates on the previous slide
are quite remarkable not just in terms
of their simplicity but their
isomorphism with the kind of message
passing we actually see in the brain so
i've just written them out again here um
just to highlight how similar they are
to things that we already use to
simulate
neuronal dynamics and message passing on
neuronal networks so for example here
the belief updates for hidden states of
the world under a particular policy any
particular point in time are just a
non-linear
function of a linear mixture of
outcomes through the likelihood matrix
and beliefs or expectations about past
states and future states that are mixed
together in the right kind of way to
give me the best expectation or guess
about
the state of the world at any particular
time policy selection is this a standard
soft max function soft mass response
function of this expected free energy
i've equipped this model with a
precision parameter which we don't need
to worry about too much for the point of
view of this talk it's interesting in
neurobiology because it seems to behave
very much like
a reward prediction error of the kind
that people who study dopamine responses
in the brain um like to think about
learning just becomes effectively
optimizing the parameters of the model
the d here are the initial states um
at the beginning of a plan or or a
policy
but the same functional form applies to
all the parameters and it looks exactly
like heading or associative plasticity
evidence accumulation in this simplest
example here and then action selection
is just selecting the most likely action
from my inferred or favorite plan
this is a slide that just describes a
simple setup a toy example i'm going to
use to illustrate the generic kinds of
behavior
that ensue
when we solve those belief update
equations or that variational message
passing um on the previous slide so this
is as simple an example um as we could
find that has both a sort of pragmatic
and epistemic bits that speak to the
intrinsic and the extrinsic value
entailed by the expected free energy
the idea here is that there is a little
mouse
it can make two moves in this team maze
um and it wants to find a red reward
that can either be in the left or the
right upper arm of the maze
but in addition there's it has the
option of going to the lower arm where
there's an instructional queue that will
tell it where the reward is so you can't
see where the reward is from its
starting point in the center so it's got
a choice it can either take a gamble and
uh 50 percent of the time be correct and
50 of the time be wrong but
i should say that once it goes into one
of the upper arms it has to stay there
these are absorbing states so there's a
50 50 chance that it will uh secure its
reward for two moves or not
or
it can choose to go and solicit the
information garner the information from
the instructional queue but it's wasting
one move
but then knows um with a fair degree of
certainty um where to go to um to get
the um
to the baited arm to get its reward so
from the point of view of an expected
utility theory or a bellman optimality
principle these two plans have the same
expected utility um of 50
but from the point of view of something
that is self-evidencing that has this
epistemic part to the objective function
the belief-based part um then clearly
it is going to be better um or it's the
animal will plan
and infer that it will be pursuing a an
epistemic policy responding to the
epistemic affordance of the
instructional cue indeed when we um
build this paradigm into a markov
decision process write down the factor
graph iterate and solve the belief
update equations that's exactly this
kind of behavior which we see so i'm
just summarizing that here
with the following graphic
the top panel just shows you the side in
which the reward was placed um this
image representation here is of the
plans that the
synthetic
mouse committed to
the degree of uncertainty at certain
times these are the outcomes um this is
if you like the um
reward or negative loss function here
and and these reflect learning as their
updates to the initial state at the
beginning of the plan namely the context
of the reward on the left or the right
and what we see is at the beginning
as we'd anticipate
um
the um the mouse goes and gets its
response to its epistemic affordance and
then goes to secure its reward and and
then what we've done is leave after the
first couple of trials the reward on
this side so as time goes on
it learns
that the context is almost uh is all is
increasingly likely to be reward on the
left hand side
and this has the effect of reducing the
epistemic or the intrinsic value the
information gain the epistemic
affordance
relative to the extrinsic
or more pragmatic part of the expected
free energy
in other words it the the the
information gain
afforded by the instructional
conditional uh conditional conditions
stimulus starts to decline
and at a particular threshold falls
below
the pragmatic or the extrinsic value at
which point the most likely behavior is
to go straight to where the little mouse
knows the reward is sitting and that's
exactly what we see at a browned trial
20 here and the
synthetic mouse goes straight to her
reward um on all occasions
so that's a basic illustration of the
deterministic um and systematic move
from exploratory behavior to
exploitative behavior
simply because
there is this dual imperative to seek
information and then seek reward or to
maintain
certain goal states but of course as you
become more familiar with an environment
after exploring it the novelty or the
salience of that environment starts to
decrease and the more pragmatic
imperatives start to emerge
um
what i'll do now
is just show you
how one can generalize this kind of
formulation to reproduce quite
sophisticated epistemic foraging of the
kind that we might engage in and i'm
going to use reading as an example uh or
a very simplified form of reading
just to emphasize
the
interesting sequelae of formulating
optimal behavior where you're putting
the sort of imperative to minimize
uncertainty into the objective function
and
how
this um
uncertainty
changes with time and with the things
that you decide to do to produce a
particular pattern and scheduling of the
way that we go and gather information
from the world so everything that
follows i'm now taking rewards away so
that we can just reveal the epistemic
nature of
sentient behavior
and i'm going to start with exactly the
same kind of markov decision process
as a generative model of outcomes so
this is a reproduction of
an earlier slide with our markov
decision process here what i'm going to
do now is just make it slightly more
interesting i'm going to add a temporal
depth i'm going to now put
a markov decision process on top of my
first markov decision process
and crucially
the higher level markov decision process
is going to unfold more slowly in time
so this higher level process from the
point of view of a generative process or
model
provides now a context that sets the
initial states for a lower process that
unfolds more quickly in time and then is
reset for a net the next context in the
next context so from the point of view
of the generative model
we're now if you like um placing
priors on
the
kinds of
behaviors that would generate the most
likely outcomes at the lower level from
the point of view of the equivalent
normal style factor graph
we can
conversely regard the lower level as
supplying evidence for which context we
are in
so
this dual exchange is implicit in the
belief updating which is just a solution
to the belief updating equations or the
variational message passing that emerges
under these deep
dictronic generative models
so the particular model that i want to
use to illustrate
the behaviors at hand
is a model of reading um but a very
simplified model where we're using sort
of iconic letters as a as opposed to a
script um so
the lowest level of the model
is sketched out here and basically what
this little agent can see
is either a particular
icon a particular letter depending upon
where she looks at different quadrants
in this word here
and the these outcomes the what and the
where aspects of the
sensed or observed outcomes are
generated by a number of hidden states
first of all the hidden state what word
is she looking at is it the word flea
which is composed of these two letters
there's a little bird next to a cat
or is it the word feed there's a little
bird next to some seed
the bird could uh eat um or is it the
word weight there's nothing next to the
little
the little um bird so this describes the
context generating the particular
outcomes at the first level so we need
to know what was the letter flea feed or
weight we'd also need to know where she
was looking at this quadrant or that
quadrant or this or that quadrant here
and just to make things interesting i've
also
put a flip in here which you can regard
um as a font change just to
make it more realistic
so that there's a degree of
generalization so given these states i
can always generate a particular set of
outcomes under a particular set of moves
moving from one to two or one to three
or three to four and and that is
sufficient to write down a factor graph
which is sufficient to define the
message passing and the self-evidencing
what about the second level right well
clearly the sequence of words this you
know the sentence that i can be um
generating um is it's uh is itself um
something that i have to specify from
the point of view of the generative
model so i have to specify well what
kinds of sentences could possibly be
generated um and i've taken three
sentences here um there's also a what
where aspect to um the the structure
here so it's what sentence is in play
that is generating the words at the
lower level or providing a contextual
prior for the words at the lower level
um and you know where am i in terms of
the word and
as part of a sequence as opposed to the
letter as a part of the word
and i can write down these hidden states
that i can generate everything i need to
know to tell me what the current
word is and um um where i am looking in
terms of
wandering through the sentence
so i've got two levels of action i can
look at the next word or i can look
around
this current word
various letters and accumulate
information as i progress through the
letters and the words and thereby
simulate reading and this is basically
what it what it looks like
um so
on the top
is a description of or
a graphic illustrating the sequence of
moves that this little agent made
whilst reading this four word sentence
flee wait feed wait here
the interesting thing about it is that
she starts off
looking around
and accumulates evidence
um
summarized here in terms of the
expectations about what's happening at
the lower level and what's happening at
the higher level so this is the second
level expectations about what sentence
she's reading and these are the first
level expectations about the particular
word in play
the interesting thing about this
simulation
is that as soon as she's certain about
the word
because if there's a cat on the um in
the on the upper row then it has to be
flea she jumps to the next word
um and after a couple of sufficient
samples to reassure her or render her
sufficiently certain that the next word
is weight that she then jumps to the
next word so what this is convincing is
exactly the kind of sparse sampling that
we actually use not just in reading but
in terms of
visually palpating the world in fact
palpating the world with all different
kinds of sense organs just to get the
information that we need in order to
resolve our uncertainty about where to
look next to build confident certain
beliefs about states of affairs out
there
and this is basically what um we wanted
to show with this with this simulation
um i just wanted to conclude by coming
back to the you know the really
interesting issues about the temporal
scheduling of this kind of die chronic
belief updating and foraging in this
instance foraging for information but um
if we put rewards in then it would be a
you know mixture a blend of foraging for
rewards and goals and information um so
what i've done here is just show the
results of the simulated belief updating
in a way that an electrophysiologist
might measure them in a real brain so at
the top we have the six sentences and i
just if you like color coded um the
weight or the expectation that we are
looking at the sentence one or sentence
four here as time progresses
during the s the planned reading of this
sentence
similarly at the lower level here are
the three alternative words that could
be seen at um
your at each
sorry
three alternative words that could be um
being looked at as
as as the agent is foraging each uh of
the letters in that word um and what and
the final panel here um are essentially
just the smoothed versions
of these
rasters of if this was simulated
electrophysiology neural activity that
can be read as local field potentials
that we can measure empirically
and notice that the
speed at which we accumulate information
about the sentence is by construction of
this dichronic deep generative model and
much slower than the the accumulation of
evidence for the word flea feed or
weight
so we see a very fast
accumulation of evidence so we're
definitely looking at flea here as soon
as we start
and then we quickly make up her mind
about the subsequent words and then move
on to the next word and slowly
accumulate evidence for the different
sentences
and there's an ambiguity here because we
have to wait until the last word to
disambiguate between sentences one and
four and indeed when we get to the last
word
this little agent can indeed confidently
um believe that she has been reading the
sentence flee weight feed and weight
i've shown the results like this because
this is exactly the kind of
neuronal dynamics that one sees
empirically when looking at this kind of
paradigm
in monkey electrophysiology so for
example here these data or this
simulation very similar to the uh the
data acquired from used electrode
recordings in this instance uh
pre-select
circadic delay period activity in the
prefrontal cortex um that is very
reminiscent of um the activity in this
uh simulation
similarly
recording fluctuations in um
electrochemical
potentials that um are one way of
measuring
the
fluctuations in neural activity um
show um a remarkable similarity between
the
synthetic and real
measurements of parasitic field
potentials potentials during active
vision um in this instance in uh i think
macaque monkey um looking at higher and
lower sorry lower and higher areas
of the visual brain
so i i'm going to finish there because
it provides a nice empirical endorsement
that the brain may actually be using
this
sort of message passing
in the service of sampling the world in
the best way possible in
in the sense of
optimal bayesian design
which
has been understood and formalized for
1950s in terms of
planning the best way
to experiment
to disclose those data that resolve the
most uncertainty about your hypotheses
so this
this notion of base optimality in terms
of the principle of best experimental
design is one way of reading the in
epistemic or the intrinsic
motivation supplied by the expected uh
the expected uh free energy
and
in that sense
um
you can
regard perception and active sensing
active perception
in exactly the same way that people like
richard gregory conceive of active
sensing and perception as hypothesis
testing that really our behavior our
sentient behavior
is in the in the game of getting the
right kind of information that resolves
our uncertainty about states of affairs
beyond our sensory organs or outside of
our skull
i'm going to give the
the final word to um to einstein just to
remember that all of this
rests upon the simple understanding and
realization that the evidence
for our models of the world can always
be split into
negative complexity of simplicity and
accuracy which just means not only in
science but also in our sentience
everything should be made as simple as
possible but not simpler
and with that all that remains is for me
to thank all the people whose ideas i've
been talking about and to thank you
for your attention and i look forward to
discussing um these
these issues with you in the near future
thank you very much indeed
thank you very much
now you have to imagine that everyone is
clapping it was a wonderful talk thank
you very much
um
i would like to
ask everyone who has questioned to to
put those in the chat and i take the
opportunity to start with the first
question so you have this wonderful
deep diacronic model would that also be
a possibility to easily
model drift and changes
in in
in
in the environment say if you have
for example seasonal changes and people
or or persons are very very very good at
adapting to that so would would you
could you do that
yes um
that's
a very interesting question in relation
to modeling the current epidemic which
is if we've actually applied these
these models to the coronavirus outbreak
and that's a very very pertinent
question yeah absolutely so i think what
you're saying there is that there are
there is a
separation of time scales at many many
levels it just keeps on going so you
what you would do in um in this
particular example is just put another
markov decision process there was an
order of magnitude slower on top of the
two levels we've already got and this
would provide um a much slower context
so there will be leaf updating
adaptation at a much much slower time
scale um
you know interesting aspect of your
question of course is what we were
looking at there is the fast belief
updating uh inferring latent or you know
hidden states of the world
the same
expected free energy and free energy
minimizing sorry maximizing elbow
maximizing dynamics when applied to the
parameters of the model give you
learning so there's also inference and
learning and the two of those go hand in
hand as well so that's another
interesting aspect and then you can even
take that further and say can you put
structure learning on top
by using the time integral of the model
evidence so now you have a a picture of
structure learning how many levels would
you want
that can be read as basic model
selection um or natural selection if
you're in biology
very interesting so we have one question
in the chat from pranav mahayan i might
summarize the first question so these
are actually two first would be whether
you could also
a model something like pavlovian fear
and risk aversion principles so how can
this reward seeking and information gain
seeking
also account for risk aversion schemes
i think it um
to
articulate um
risk aversion and risk sensitivity
within this framework is is relatively
straightforward so all you do is you
rewrite your cost function or your
reward function as a log probability so
i i was talking about sort of prior
preferences so um you just take the
logarithm of that and then you have a
continuous variable that goes from plus
to minus infinity that
scores your um
your the the value or the extrinsic
value of a particular outcome
once you've done that
then you get all these sort of natural
behaviors um that one would see in
reinforcement learning
with the added
benefit that now you can measure your
reward
um or your utility in natural units
because now you've expressed your
utility as a log probability so if you
use natural logarithms you've got
natural units which interestingly have
the same units as information so now
you've got the value of information you
can either say well this bit of
information is worth three dollars or
three dollars is worth this amount of
information
and the way that you balance the two
is effectively um by ascribing a
precision
an inverse variance to to those belief
distributions so once you've written
down your reward in terms of
probabilistic preferences
now you can make them quantitatively
bigger or smaller by making them more or
less precise so if i'm very very
confident a very precise beliefs i like
these things and i don't like those
that will dominate the
um pragmatic or the expected utility
part of the expected free energy
and that will suppress possibly the risk
aspect whereas if i have very very
imprecise i don't have any confident
beliefs about what i find rewarding my
subjective utility if you like um then
it's likely that i might become more
sensitized to the to you know to to the
uh the ambiguity term and i might become
more um careful um i want to resolve
ambiguity um and be less sensitive to
the um or act as if i was
less worried about the risks because i'm
less confident about what i find
rewarding so really interesting question
you know in principle you should be able
to fit the precisions in order to make
them match exactly with economic
sort of
forms of risk aversion and
the like
there's another question in the chat so
um this would be the question about your
views on including or how including
emotional balance into the framework and
the suggestion would be whether first
and second derivative for free energy
would would fit that or what would be
your view on that
well
that's a challenging question and
certainly people have um
have proposed for many years now that
the sort of you know
the rate of change of free energy as a
score
in terms of how well you are engaging
with your world um is is a nice valence
measure of um that could predict your
your emotional status um i think that's
a useful um
heuristic however i think the the you
know the more direct answer to this is
um it's all in the uncertainty you know
if you estimate and you predict that you
are now in a context of an environment
in a situation
where your uncertainty about what to do
is irreducible that's going to make you
feel anxious and bad
so you know the good feelings the aha
moments the realization oh yes i won
that lottery or it's me it's it's dinner
time or it's my favorite sitcom
all of these things when you feel good
and happy
all come along with this collapse of
uncertainty and the way four becomes
very very clear
um so in a sense that is if you like an
anticipation of a
you're an improvement in the free energy
but that has to be represented in the
genetic model you know
it has to be part of your belief
structure in your belief system and your
representation of the world and it looks
as if that is um the closest um
thing in the generative model to that
kind of monitoring the fluctuations in
how well i'm doing in terms of the free
energy seems to be the precision of
beliefs about what i'm doing which is of
course the dopamine um
you know what we think it might be the
thing that dopamine registers so
the
at a very simple level of just valence
your things being good and bad
i would ascribe that to
the precision of beliefs about what i'm
going to do so when things get better
that basically means i can see the way
ahead clearly
thank you so i'm looking a bit at the
time so i i expect although there would
be more questions we have to stop here
because the time is small is over and we
expect the next speaker to be here in in
like
two minutes
so thanks
from everyone attending the session for
this excellent talk and discussion and
we hope every
to be able to see
everyone and you also in particular in
the near future in person thank you well
thank you very much
bye bye
you